Guide to the Sorotick Family Photographs and Papers 1943-1992 PR 349
New-York Historical Society
Sorotick Family photographs and papers
1943-1992
New-York Historical Society
Sorotick, Marsha
Sorotick, Irving, 1915-2000
PR 349
0.209 Linear feet (1 box)
112 photographs sent home from Europe by Irving Sorotick (1915-2000), a United States Army veteran of World War II, plus material relating to the presidency of John F. Kennedy, notably a high school project scrapbook assembled by Sorotick's daughter, Marsha, during the Cuban Missile Crisis of October 1962. Also includes seven political campaign pins.
Arrangement
Items in this small collection are grouped by topic--World War II, John F. Kennedy, and political campaign pins--and organized chronologically.
Biographical/Historical Note
Irving Sorotick (1915–2000) was a United States Army veteran of World War II who enlisted at New York on 17 August 1943 and was discharged on 11 January 1946. He sent some 112 photographs of his time in Europe back home to his wife, Pearl. Judging by those shots dated June 1944 and identified as "Omaha Beach" (a code name for one of the five sectors of the Allied invasion of German-occupied France), Sorotick may have participated in the Normandy landings of 6 June 1944. But the casualness of the photographs suggests he probably arrived shortly after the D-Day invasions (see Folder 1).
Sorotick's daughter, Marsha, attended Martin Van Buren High School in Queens, New York, during John F. Kennedy's presidency.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Marsha Sorotick, August 2017 (accession no. PPAC.2017.051), and September 2018 (accession no. PPAC.2018.054).
Scope and Contents
The collection includes 112 photographs Irving Sorotick sent home from Europe to his wife, Pearl, during his World War II U.S. Army service. Fifty-two of the images are dated, as is a letter (20 September 1944) he wrote on stationery printed with views of Parisian landmarks.
Marsha Sorotick's contributions to the collection include the JFK scrapbook she assembled in high school during the Cuban Missile Crisis of October 1962, as well as the 22 November 1963 issue of the New York World-Telegram and the Sun announcing "PRESIDENT SHOT DEAD," plus five photographs taken at a traveling exhibition of JFK memorabilia.
Seven political campaign pins--ranging from 1960 ("Kennedy for President") to 1992 ("Elect Clinton | Gore")--round out the collection.
Accruals
The bulk of the collection was donated by Marsha Sorotick in August 2017 (accession no. PPAC.2017.051). Ms. Sorotick supplied an additional photograph (a 1968 view of a newsstand at East 23rd Street and Park Avenue South) in September 2018 (accession no. PPAC.2018.054).
Vice-Presidential candidates -- United States.; Presidential candidates -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- Participation, American; Cuban Missile Crisis, 1962.; Photographic prints.; Slides (photographs).; Ephemera.; Scrapbooks.; Mayors -- New York (State) -- New York.; Gore, Al, 1948-; Clinton, Bill, 1946-; Bentsen, Lloyd; Dukakis, Michael S. (Michael Stanley), 1933-; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Lindsay, John V. (John Vliet); Chisholm, Shirley, 1924-2005; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963
- WWII: photographs (52) (dated), 1944 May-1945 August (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Locations include England, France (Cherbourg, "Omaha Beach," Mortain), Belgium, Holland, Germany (Cologne, Nuremberg), and Monaco.
- WWII: photographs (56 + 4 slides) (undated), [1944-1945] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  Locations include England, France (Marseille, Reims, "Camp Chicago"), Germany (Roosevelt Rhine River Bridge), Holland, and the United States (Camp Patrick Henry, Virginia).
- WWII: ephemera, 1944, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  A letter from Irving Sorotick to his wife, Pearl, dated Paris, 20 September 1944, on stationery printed with photographs of Parisian landmarks. With two undated postcards of Chartres and Cherbourg.
- WWII: newspaper | New York Herald Tribune, 1945 January 27 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  Front page of the European edition of the New York Herald Tribune, published at Paris, with the headline "Russians in 18-Mile Breakthrough Reach Shores of Gulf of Danzig; 7th Army Halts Germans in Alsace."
- JFK: scrapbook, 1962 October-November (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  In October 1962, Marsha Sorotick (donor of the collection) was a sophomore at Martin Van Buren High School in Queens, New York. For an American History class, she was assigned to create this scrapbook of President Kennedy's activities during one week. It turned out to be the period of the Cuban Missile Crisis. Sorotick got a A+.
- JFK: newspaper | New York World-Telegram and the Sun, 1963 November 22 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  Headline: "PRESIDENT SHOT DEAD."
  Access Restrictions
  Too brittle for use.
- JFK: photographs (5), 1964 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  In June 1964, Marsha Sorotick (donor of the collection) visited and photographed a display of JFK memorabilia at the IBM Building (590 Madison Avenue, Manhattan). The exhibition traveled to twenty-three cities to raise funds for the construction of the JFK Presidential Library in Boston.
- JFK: souvenir journal, [1964] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  The President Nobody Knew, vol. 1, no. 1, the Remember November Issue.
- Political campaign pins (7), 1960-1992 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  Missing Title
  Kennedy for President [1960]
  LBJ for the USA [1964]
  Catalyst for Change | Shirley Chisholm for President [1972]
  Lindsay 72 [1972]
  Dukakis | Bentsen [1988]
  Elect Clinton | Gore 92 [1992]
  CWA for Clinton | Gore [1992]
- Newsstand photograph, 1968 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  This photograph was taken by the donor, Marsha Sorotick, in the autumn of 1968. According to information she supplied by letter (5 September 2018), "it shows the corner of E. 23rd St. and Park Ave. South. It looked very much the same until about 2-3 years ago when a sidewalk elevator leading down into the subway was constructed and, alas, the newsstand wasn't returned. The 'Time' magazine cover [visible in the photograph] is of the events in Prague. I believe at the time I worked nearby at the NYPD Academy library."